SILU WANG

Email: siluwang.evo@gmail.com Website: https://www.silurianwang.net

RESEARCH INTEREST

In order to substantially understand biodiversity in the changing world, I investigate the genomic footprints of hybridization, adaptation, and the evolution of reproductive isolation over various temporal and spatial scales. My ultimate research goal is integrating population-focused, processing-driven insights for effective species rescue in the 6th extinction.

ACADEMIC POSITIONS

Postdoc + Jan. 2020 - Dec. 2021 University of California, Berkeley (UC Berkeley)

Project: The role of sex chromosome evolution in fruit fly speciation Mentor: Doris Bachtrog, Center of Theoretical and Evolutionary Biology

+ Jan. 2022 - Dec. 2022 University of California, Davis (UC Davis)

Project: Speciation-introgression spatial genomics in wood warblers

Mentor: Graham Coop, Center of Population Biology

EDUCATION

PhD Zoology, 2020.

Thesis: Genomic architecture of speciation in a warbler species complex

Advisor: Darren Irwin, University of British Columbia (UBC)

Committee members: Sally Otto, Loren Rieseberg, Dolph Schluter

MA Ecology, Evolution & Behavior; Computer Science (minor), 2014.

Thesis: Behavior, morphology, and genetic signatures of sexual selection in poeciliid fish

Advisor: Molly Cummings, University of Texas at Austin (UT Austin)

Committee members: Mike Ryan, Hans Hofmann

BS Behavior, Genetics & Neurobiology; Applied Statistics (minor), high distinction, 2011.

Thesis: Aggressive behaviors, food-deprivation, and the foraging gene

Advisor: Marla Sokolowski, University of Toronto (U of T)

PUBLICATIONS (*corresponding author; +equal contribution; ^undergraduate mentee)

- (11) Price S., Schumer M., **Wang S.**, Young R., Cummings M.* Individual variation in preference and affiliative behavior in sailfin fish refines the neurotranscriptomic pathway for mate preference. *Submitted*.
- (10) Wang S.* Coevolution of song and egg coloration: multimodal mating signals? BioRxiv.
- (9) de Zwaan D. R., Mackenzie J. ^, Mikkelsen E.^ , Wood, C., **Wang S.*** Opposing dominance within a color gene block is associated with maladaptive hybrid signal discordance. *BioRxiv*.
- (8) **Wang S.**, Nalley M.J., Chatla K., Aldaimalani R., MacPherson A., Wei KH-C., Corbett R., Mai D., Bachtrog D.* Neo-sex chromosome evolution shapes sex-dependent asymmetrical introgression barrier. *BioRxiv. In revision. PNAS*.
- (7) +MacPherson A.*, +Wang S. Rieseberg L., Yamaguchi R., Otto S. Parental population isolation and

Updated: Nov. 15th, 2021

range expansion before secondary contact leads to greater hybrid relative fitness. <u>BioRxiv</u>. **Accepted. American Naturalist**.

- (6) Wang S.*, Ore M. Mikkelsen E.^, Lee-Yaw, J., Rohwer S., Irwin DE. 2021. Signatures of mitonuclear climate adaptation in a warbler species complex. *Nature Communications*. 12:4279.
- (5) **Wang S.***, Rohwer S., de Zwaan D. R., Toews D.P.L., Lovette I.J., Mackenzie J. ^, Irwin DE. **2020**. Selection on a small genomic region underpins differentiation in multiple color traits between two warbler species. *Evolution Letters*. 4-6: 502-515.
- (4) **Wang S.***, Rohwer S., Delmore K., Irwin DE. **2019**. Cross-decades stability of an avian hybrid zone. *Journal of Evolutionary Biology*. 32: 1242–1251.
- (3) **Wang S.**, Sokolowski M. B.* **2017**. Aggressive behaviors, food-deprivation and the *foraging* gene. *Royal Society Open Science*. 4:170042.
- (2) **Wang S.***, Cummings M. E., Kirkpatrick M. A. **2015**. Coevolution of male courtship and sexual conflict characters in mosquitofish. *Behavioral Ecology*. 26:1013-1020.
- (1) **Wang S.M.T.**, Ramsey M., Cummings M. E.* **2014**. Plasticity of the mate choice mind: courtship evokes choice-like brain responses in females from a coercive mating system. *Genes, Brain and Behavior*. 13:365-375.

INVITED PRESENTATIONS

- 2021 Museum Seminar Series, Museum of Natural Sciences, Louisiana State University
- 2021 Advances in the Study of Reproductive Isolation in birds Symposium (AOS meeting).
- **2021** Barton Group, Institute of Science and Technology Austria.
- **2021** Evolution, Genomics, Behavioral Ecology, French National Centre for Scientific Research.
- 2021 Evolution, Ecology, Genetics, and Genomics, University of Rochester.
- 2021 Center of Population Biology, UC Davis
- 2020 Population Genetics seminar, Duke University.
- **2020** Ornithology Discussion, University of New Mexico.
- **2019** Center of Theoretical Evolutionary Genomics seminar, UC Berkeley.
- 2019 Les Ecologistes seminar, Simon Fraser University.
- **2018** BLISS seminar, University of British Columbia.
- 2013 Lunch seminar, School of Geological Science, UT Austin.
- 2013 Brain, Behavior & Evolution (BBE) Seminar, UT Austin.
- **2013** Biology Department Seminar, University of Oklahoma.
- 2012 BBE Seminar, UT Austin.

ORAL PRESENTATIONS

- 2021 American Ornithological Society (AOS) meeting, Virtual
- **2021** The Society for the Study of Evolution meeting, Virtual
- 2021 Population Genomics Journal Club, UC Berkeley, Virtual
- **2021** Annual Drosophila Research Conference, The Genetics Society of America, Virtual
- 2019 The Society for the Study of Evolution meeting, Providence, Rhode Island, USA.
- 2019 Eco-Evo Retreat, Brackendale, BC, Canada.
- **2018** International Ornithological Congress meeting, Vancouver, BC, Canada.
- 2017 The Society for the Study of Evolution meeting, Portland, OR, USA.
- **2017** Canadian Society for Ecology and Evolution meeting, Victoria, BC, Canada.

Updated: Nov. 15th, 2021

- 2016 North American Ornithological Congress, Washington, DC, USA.
- 2015 American Ornithologists' Union & Cooper's Ornithological Society meeting, OK, USA.
- **2014** International Ornithological Congress, Tokyo, Japan.
- 2014 American Society of Naturalists meeting, Pacific Grove, CA, USA.
- **2014** Society for Integrative and Comparative Biology Meeting, Austin, TX, USA.
- **2012** The Society for the Study of Evolution, Ottawa, ON, Canada.
- 2012 Animal Behavior Society meeting, Albuquerque, NM, USA.
- 2012 Integrative Biology Graduate Symposium, UT Austin.
- 2011 American Ornithologists' Union, Jacksonville, FL, USA.

POSTERS (*best poster award)

- 2019* The Society for the Study of Evolution, Providence, RI, USA.
- 2018 Evo-Wibo Conference, Port Townsend, WA, USA.
- **2018** Evo-Eco Department Retreat, Brackendale, BC, Canada.
- **2018*** UBC Zoology Graduate Spring Symposium, Vancouver, BC, Canada.
- 2017 The Society for the Study of Evolution Meeting, Portland, OR, USA.
- 2017* UBC Zoology Graduate Symposium, Vancouver, BC, Canada.
- 2010 Ontario Biology Day, Toronto, ON, Canada.
- **2010** Crime Prevention Conference, Mississauga, ON, Canada.

AWARDS GRANTS & HONORS

		4
2019	Ruth Patrick Student Poster Award, American Society of Naturalists	\$1,000
2019	Zoology Travel Award, Department of Zoology, UBC	\$500
2019	Best Talk Award, Eco-Evo Retreat, Brackendale, BC	
2018-2019	Zoology Graduate Fellowship, UBC	\$16,000
2018	Gibson's citation, Green College, UBC	
2018	Best Poster Award, Zoology Graduate Spring Symposium	
2018	Graduate Student Travel Fund, UBC	\$500
2017	Best Poster Award, Zoology Graduate Spring Symposium	
2016	Werner and Hildegard Hesse Research Award in Ornithology	\$2,500
2015-2018	Postgraduate Scholar ship D (PGS D) Natural Sciences and Engineering	
	Research Council of Canada (NSERC) \$63,000	
2015	Werner and Hildegard Hesse Research Award in Ornithology	\$3,500
2014	Biodiversity Research: Integrative Training & Education Grant, UBC	\$4,000
2014	R Howard Webster Foundation Fellowship, UBC	\$2,500
2014-2018	Four Year Doctoral Fellowship, UBC	\$18,000
2014	Student Travel grant, International Ornithological Congress	\$500
2014	Travel grant, Ecology, Evolution and Behavior, UT Austin	\$1,000
2012-2013	Texas Ecolab Research Grant	\$3,000
2011	Student Travel Award, American Ornithologists' Union	\$600
2011	Ontario Graduate Scholarship, Ministry of Training,	
	Colleges and Universities of Ontario	\$6,000
2011	Excellence Award in the Natural Sciences and Engineering, U of T	\$5,600
2010, 2011	Honor Roll in Department of Mathematical and Computational Science	s, U of T
2010	Student Membership Award, American Ornithologists' Union	
	·	

TEACHING/MENTORING EXPERIENCE

Teach assistance

• BIOL336: Fundamentals of Evolution Biology, UBC

Updated: Nov. 15th, 2021

• BIO321: Introduction to Computational Biology, UT Austin 2014 Spring

• BIO370: Evolution, UT Austin 2012 Spring, 2013 Fall

BIO311: Introductory Biology, UT Austin
BIO206: Structure & Function of Organisms, UT Austin
BIO318: Biostatistics, UT Austin
STA257: Probability and Statistics I, U of T
BIO329: Mammalian Biology field section, U of T
2012 Fall
2011 Fall
2010 Fall
2009 Fall

Guest lecture

BIOL427: Ornithology and Herpetology 2019 Fall, 2021 Spring

Mentoring

Anton Pederson: 2012; Arvind Pillai: 2013; Korey Conley: 2013-14;

Ruth Midgley: 2015; Else Mikkelsen: 2016-17; Jacqueline Mackenzie: 2017; Reema Aldaimalani 2021

TEACHING SKILLS

Field ornithology: banding, mist-netting, measurements, blood and feather sampling, song recording and analyses, plumage pigment study, field behavioral experiments

Computational biology: coding and statistical analyses in R, spatial genomics, bioinformatics in Unix

Molecular lab: DNA or RNA extraction, library preparation

Scientific Illustration: data visualization, vector illustration, watercolor and pencil drawing poster and infographics

OTHER ACADEMIC CONTRIBUTION

Leadership &/or coordination

2020-present	Speciation & Introgression Genomics Discussion Group, coordinator, UC Berkeley	
	i.e. weekly international zoom seminar-discussion group of over 470 researchers	
2017-19	Biodiversity Seminar Committee, A/V coordinator, Biodiversity Research Center, UBC	
2018	Dining Society Treasurer, Green College, UBC	
2017-18	Sustainability Committee, Chair, Green College, UBC	
2015-16	Art Committee, Chair, Green College, UBC	

Reviewer service

Auk, American Naturalist, Genome Biology and Evolution, Integrative and Comparative Biology, Molecular Ecology, National Science Foundation Grant Proposal, Poland National Science Center Grant Proposal.

OUTREACH

2021	Breaking Language Barriers in Biodiversity Science, guest mentor, UC Berkeley
2019	Girls in Science Technology Engineering and Math (STEM), mentor, Templeton
	Secondary School, Vancouver
2019	Nature Illustration Club Coordinator, UBC
2015-19	Biodiversity Birding Group Coordinator, UBC

Public lectures

- On the Speciation of Species: the Fantastic Process Underlying Biodiversity, Mar. 26th 2018, Green College, UBC.
- The Hermit Expedition: Stories about the Habitat, Flora, Fauna and People in Northwest America, **Sep. 26**th **2016**, Green College, UBC.
- The Scales of Existence: A Journey from Population to Molecules (Collaborated with Isobel Mouat, Microbiology and Immunology; Kelsey Huus, Microbiology and Immunology; J. Andrew Alexander, Biochemistry and Molecular Biology), Nov. 16th 2015, UBC.
- Sassy Tastes or Sexy Traits: Stories about Coevolution of Female Preference and Male Traits. Darwin's 203rd Birthday, **May11**th **2012**, Texas Memorial Museum